Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, we start a new מסכת נדרים, Masechet
Nedarim, and which is about taking vows, and I'll say one word
very briefly about what a נדר neder is and then I'll say
a few words about what some unique aspects of the מסכת Masechet
and then we'll actually start reading it. It's a short דף daf
because there's a big ר"ן Ran here.
So a נדר neder in the תורה, Torah, there are two ways
a person takes vows in the תורה, Torah, there's a שבועה, shvuah,
we just had שבועות, Shvuos, so not the same שבועה shvuah but
I mentioned that because of לא תשא שם ה' לשוא lo tissa
shem Hashem lashav or ולא תשבעו בשמי לשקר, v’lo tishavu bishmi lashaker,
swearing in God's name. A שבועה shvuah is about an action. You
take an oath that you have done something in the past or
have not. You can be made to swear about monetary matters, I
borrowed this money, I didn't borrow money, I saw this testimony relating
to somebody, etc. And a שבועה shvuah could be about something you're
going to do in the future. I take an oath that I
will give you a hundred dollars, I take an oath that I
will not eat any bread tomorrow. Okay, or that I won't do
something, I will do something, etc. That's what a שבועה shvuah is.
A נדר, neder, now, in the תורה, Torah, it's not so clear
that a נדר neder is that much different than a שבועה. shvuah.
For example, you have יעקב אבינו, Yaakov Avinu, which says וידר יעקב
נדר לאמר אם יהיה אלהים עמדי ושמרני בדרך הזה אשר אנכי הולך
ונתן לי לחם לאכול ובגד ללבש ושבתי
בשלום אל בית אבי והיה ה' לי לאלהים והאבן הזאת אשר שמתי
מצבה יהיה בית אלהים וכל אשר תתן לי עשר אעשרנו לך.
Vayidor Yaakov neder lemor im yihiyeh elohim imadi ushmarani baderech hazeh asher
anochi holech v’nasan li lechem
leechol u’beged lilbosh v’shavti v’shalom el beis avi v’hayah Hashem li lelohim
v’ha’even hazos asher samti matzeivah yihiyeh beis elohim v’chol asher titten li
asser a’assrenu lach. I'll make this into an altar, I'll give you
a tithe, okay, that sounds a lot like a שבועה. shvuah. You
say if something happens, I will do so and so, you're taking
an oath about doing something. And it's not clear maybe the difference
is is that it doesn't use God's name, a שבועה shvuah is
with God's name classically. Well, no, but it doesn't say a נדר
בשם ה'. neder b’shem Hashem. A שבועה shvuah is you're calling upon
God, the nature of a שבועה shvuah is you're calling upon God
to testify. As God is my witness, so and so did not
happen, I will do, okay,
I can't fully unpack that. Okay, but anyway, God even takes a
שבועה shvuah in His own name,
so there's a sense of calling upon God to testify that something
about something that you have done or something that you will do.
So a שבועה shvuah is about taking God's name and therefore taking
God's name in vain if it's a false שבועה. shvuah. A נדר
neder in the simple sense of the פסוקים pesukim is not necessarily
that different in the sense that it might be about doing something,
but it doesn't seem to focus on God's name as God is
my witness and there seems more to be an element, at least
in the case by יעקב, Yaakov, of a sense of giving something,
like I'm going to give something to God, there's some sense of
a
religious gift or contribution that's being made. So you also have קרבנות,
korbanot, קרבנות korbanot are a נדר neder or a נדבה, nedavah, if
a קרבן korban is a נדר neder or a נדבה. nedavah. So
what is, but that's not exactly how חז"ל Chazal understood it. And
the other classic place that you have נדר neder is
by what do you call it, at מטות, Mattos,
yeah,
by מטות.
Mattos. איש כי ידר נדר לה' או השבע שבעה לאסר אסר על
נפשו לא יחל דברו ככל היצא מפיו יעשה. Ish ki yidor neder
l’Hashem o hishava shvuah le'esor issar al nafsho lo yachel devaro kechol
hayotze mipiv ya'aseh. He takes a נדר neder or a שבועה shvuah
to make something forbidden. He has to do what he said. ואשה
כי תדר נדר לה' ואסרה אסר בבית אביה בנעריה. V'ishah ki sador
neder l’Hashem v’assrah issar b’veis aviha b’neureha. And she makes something forbidden,
and her father hears, and he annuls it, etc, etc. So here
it speaks about making something forbidden, okay, but it connects it also
to a שבועה. shvuah. So again, it's not so clear that you
would have seen it as necessarily different, again maybe a שבועה shvuah
is בשם ה', b’shem Hashem, maybe it's just the terminology use, but
nevertheless, חז"ל Chazal
identify that a נדר neder is something else. A נדר neder is
basically focusing, and we're going to say this on our first דף,
daf, focusing on the object, whereas a שבועה shvuah focuses on the
person and an action. So whereas a שבועה shvuah is someone says
takes a שבועה shvuah that they will not eat something or they
will eat something, a נדר neder can't, is that this object becomes
a forbidden type of an object. That's the concept of a נדר,
neder, making the object forbidden. Okay, now, so it doesn't work with
יעקב. Yaakov. So what we have to do is we have to
take the cases in the תורה Torah where נדר neder sounds
like often נדרים Nedarim, are if God does this for me, isn't
it וידר ישראל נדר לאמר אם נתן תתן את העם הזה בידי
והחרמתי את עריהם? Vayidor Yisrael neder lemor im nason titten es ha'am
hazeh b'yadi v'hacharamti es areihem? So often it sounds like a category,
God, if you help me and if you're there for me, I
will give this to you, I'll dedicate this to you, that becomes
a different category called נדרי מצוה, nidrei mitzvah, taking a נדר neder
to do a מצוה, mitzvah, and that's really like a שבועה. shvuah.
Okay, even that's not exactly like the נדר neder in the תורה
Torah which is more like giving something to God. Okay, so somebody
said takes a נדר neder that they're going to learn a hundred
דף daf tomorrow or do the דף היומי, Daf Hayomi, that becomes
נדרי מצוה. nidrei mitzvah. Okay, but then, but so it doesn't really
fit the evidence in the תורה, Torah, we make that a different
נדר, neder, there's also
a נדר neder of a קרבן. korban. A נדר Neder of a
קרבן Korban is that you basically take an obligation upon yourself to
bring a קרבן, Korban, right? So if you just were to focus
on the object, you were sanctifying an animal, that's more like a
נדבה. Nedava. A נדר Neder is an obligation on yourself. So classic
נדרים nedarim really are I will give this to God and are
an obligation on yourself, and that's what you have by a קרבן,
Korban, and that's what you have by נדרי מצוה. Nidrei Mitzvah. But
this entire מסכת masechet doesn't focus on that. This entire מסכת Masechet
focuses on the emphasis of נדרים Nedarim as it appears in פרשת
מטות, Parshat Matos, which is making an object forbidden. Okay, so again
what you have is you have
a
שבועה, Shvuah,
which is like an oath. It's basically I will do or
not do or I have done, have done,
whatever, didn't do
X, and it's usually in God's name. Okay? That tends to be
a big part of the idea of שבועה, Shvuah, in God's name,
right, as God is my witness. That's a שבועה. Shvuah. Okay, a
נדר Neder in the תורה Torah you've got like וידר יעקב נדר.
Vayidar Yaakov
Neder.
You have, what is it, what's the פסוק? Pasuk? וידר ישראל נדר?
Vayidar Yisrael Neder? Yes. וידר ישראל נדר, Vayidar Yisrael Neder, right?
אשר שמתי מצבה יהיה בית אלקים וכל אשר תתן לי,
תתן לי עשר אעשרנו לך,
Asher samti matzeva yiheyeh beis elokim vechol
asher titein li, titein li aser a'asrenu lach, I'll give it to
you. Okay? And here is והחרמתי את עריהם, Vehacharamti es areihem, which
is also seems to be some type of gift to God,
את עריהם. Es areihem. So here you have a sense of basically
some sense of a gift to God. Okay, if God does something
for me, I'll give something to God. You also have נדר Neder
of a קרבנות, Korbanot, right? אם נדר או נדבה זבח קרבנו, Im
neder o nedava zevach korbano, אם נדר או נדבה זבח קרבנו.
Im neder o
nedava zevach korbano. Okay, so there you have it also as a
obligation to give a קרבן, Korban, to give a קרבן. Korban. And
then all of that you have by פרשת מטות, Parshat Matos, this
becomes the paradigm for the entire מסכת, Masechet פרשת מטות, Parshat Matos,
where it's איש כי ידר נדר, Ish ki yidor neder, איש, Ish,
what is it?
איש כי ידר נדר או השבע שבועה לאסור
איסר
על נפשו.
Ish ki yidor neder o hishava shvuah
le'esor issar al
nafsho.
So it's about making something forbidden. And this becomes, and although it's
also connected to a שבועה, Shvuah, you can make something forbidden by
saying I won't eat it, right? But it could be I take
an oath that I won't eat something. So nevertheless, what we do
is we focus and we say the key idea of a נדר,
Neder, at least that we're going to be discussing is, you make
an object forbidden. Not, it's not about you, it's about the object.
The object becomes a forbidden object. Okay, this object should be forbidden
on me, or this object should be forbidden on Michael, if it's
focusing on the object, you can even make it forbidden to somebody
else. Okay?
As long as it's yours.
Okay. So that becomes the focus of נדר. Neder. These things here,
which is all the heavy evidence in the תורה Torah become essentially
conceptual exceptions. This becomes not necessarily about a gift, this becomes translated
halachically into נדרי מצוה, Nidrei Mitzvah, which is not necessarily like giving
an object, it could be a guy says a נדר Neder I'll
learn a hundred דף גמרא Daf Gemara or something. And this, the
נדר Neder of a קרבן Korban remains the standard, נדר Neder of
a קרבן. Korban. And the סתם Stam idea, the blank idea of
a נדר Neder is this case in מטות. Matos. Okay? This case
of this object will be forbidden to me, even though the word
also says a שבועה. Shvuah. So שבועה Shvuah becomes in God's name
I will or won't or haven't done something etc., right, as God
is my witness type of a thing, and a נדר Neder is
this object is forbidden to me. Now in that way there is
some something similar to this idea, if you want to see a
common theme here about that. If you are giving a מעשר Maaser
to God, or you are making the cities חרם, Cherem, which is
like also some type of a given over to God, right? Well,
the way you take מעשר Maaser is by verbally doing something and
your words change the status of the object. If you were to
make an object חרם Cherem to God, you would say this object
is חרם, Cherem, your words would change the status. The way you
give something, these types of things to God, is by affecting the
status, effecting the status of the object. Okay? Similarly when I make
an animal a קרבן, Korban, okay, although נדר Neder starts with I'm
obligated, but then I separate it out as the קרבן, Korban, I
have effected, I have you know transformed the status of this object
into something holy through my words. So that at least is a
common denominator and that gets us to the idea of making the
object forbidden, right? I say this object is a... forbidden object, my
words transformed the identity and the status of the object. So if
you wanted to see a common theme, right, even if some of
these start with personal obligations, they all have some object that becomes
the focus of them that is changed its status and given to
like these are given to God, okay, this might not be given
to God, but it becomes a forbidden object. So my words make
the object a forbidden object and that genuinely is a theme that
runs through here, and I just want to add one point to
this, if here the key is God's name, that's the key, maybe
we should use a different color, I don't have a different color,
here's a different color.
Okay,
so if the key here is God's name and I, that's the
key, here the key is the object and it's not the use
of God's name, but the key here is the object and it
is אין נודרים אלא בדבר הנדור
Ein nodrin ela
bedavar hanadur means that here you call on God to witness that
you have or will do something, here what you say is this
object should be like a קרבן. Korban. You use the paradigm, the
model of where I know that my words can change the status
of an object and make it forbidden. If I say this object
should be like
חזיר, Chazir, is a נדר Neder this object is like חזיר, Chazir,
I haven't said anything, okay, because חזיר Chazir is something that God
made forbidden. That's not in the realm of anything that my words
have any effect. I can't make something חזיר, Chazir, only its genetic
makeup or God, you know, whatever, can make it חזיר. Chazir. I
can't make it forbidden. If I say this object should be like
a קרבן, Korban, then I am drawing on, I'm hearkening to, right,
that realm in which I have the power to change the status
of an object. So the same way I can make something חרם
Cherem or מעשר Ma'aser or a נדר Neder or a קרבן, Korban,
I can make this object forbidden. So here it is דבר הנדור.
Davar Hanadur. Here I use God's name to say that I will
do something, here I say the object is forbidden just like this
other type of forbidden object that we know that I have the
power to make, so a classic example of that would be קרבן.
Korban. And therefore that would be a classic example of that and
therefore the classic word for נדר Neder and this is going to
get to our first משנה Mishna is the word קונם. Konam. קונם
Konam is a sort of a euphemism or whatever, a variation of
the word קרבן. Korban. קונם דבר זה עלי Konam davar zeh alay
means this thing should be like a קרבן Korban to me, okay,
and therefore and that's what that is drawing on. Okay, is that
clear again? What the way it develops is this I call on
God to be my witness that I have done something, I will
do something, I'm doing this in God's name. Here I am starts
with all these things I'm giving to God, but then it gets
focused on, okay, it's a thing that's being given to God, your
words are transforming an object. We know you can do that by
קרבנות, Korbanot, we know you can do that by taking תרומות ומעשרות,
Terumot u'Ma'asrot, there's a whole realm of areas of where your words
can transform an object, most seriously by a קרבן Korban that really
makes it off limits and forbidden. And therefore this focuses on making
an object forbidden and using the concept like some like a object
that is a דבר הנדור, Davar Hanadur, like an object that my
words we know can make forbidden, like classic examples like a קרבן
Korban and hence the word קונם. Konam. So okay, this focuses not
on God, but on actually me if you want, my power, my
words' power to make an object forbidden and therefore uses the idea
of like a קרבן. Korban. Yes.
So if you permission I just want to challenge this a little
bit, only because when I look at the first two, for instance
מעשר. Ma'aser. I'm listening, yeah. In my mind the paradigm is an
action, right, כל אשר יעבור תחת השבט יהיה קודש לה', Kol asher
ya'avor tachat hashevet yiheyeh kodesh l'Hashem, something happens, I'm doing some. Yeah,
basically and also like for
לזכרים, Lezacharim, הבאים כאור מתישבים והנחץ, Haba'in k'or mityashvim v'hanachatz, they do
something.
Right. So that you might be right, you know, it might be
that I'm just sort of doing it in
in חז"ל's Chazal way of understanding those concepts, they come much more
through words than through actions, you know, and if you could say
you could say מעשר, Ma'aser, you know, the tenth at the top
northern part of this כרי Kri is of this pile of wheat
is מעשר, Ma'aser, it's all by words. So how much, you know,
but you also have נזיר כי יפליא לנדור נדר נזיר. Nazir ki
yaflia lindor neder nazir. So it's an interesting question, okay, but definitely
in חז"ל's Chazal understanding all of these are effectively done by words.
Yes.
But I can't actually do an action and make it be forbidden?
Like if I put it, you know.
No, no, you need to there's a question maybe no, you need
to actually be מוציא בפה. Motzi b'peh. I mean there's a few
places where maybe just מחשבה Machshava without מוציא בפה, Motzi b'peh, but
the key is the emphasis is מוציא בפה. Motzi b'peh. And that's
the act of הפלאה, Hafla'ah, הפלאה Hafla'ah which is what we're going
to be dealing with נדרים, Nedarim נזיר, Nazir, whatever's all going to
be acts of speech acts that effect a change in status. And
that by the way, right, שבועה Shevuah doesn't really effect a change
in a status of a thing as opposed to if you make
yourself a נזיר, Nazir, you give a קרבן, Korban, you take מעשר,
Ma'aser, you make a נדר, Neder, you make. Those are all called
הפלאה, hafala, כי יפלי לנדור נדר נזיר, ki yafli lindor neder nazir,
which basically means enunciate, but essentially it means a speech act that
transforms the status of something. Yes, right.
Does the דבר הנדור davar hanadur become forbidden without an expression of
קונם? konam?
Right, because but you still say, you might say הרי זה עולה,
harei zeh olah, you don't need to say the word קונם konam
because you're making it a קרבן korban through saying a קרבן korban
word.
But I'm saying, but I'm saying without the expression of קרבן, korban,
if you're saying עולה, olah, so exactly. So I'm asking if a
דבר הנדור davar hanadur can become forbidden without an expression of קונם.
konam.
Yes, you could say הרי זה עלי כעולה. harei zeh alai k'olah.
Okay.
What do you mean? Or what if you say הרי זה אסור
עלי? harei zeh assur alai?
Okay, so we'll get to that. You might not need to to
articulate the דבר הנדור, davar hanadur, it might be implied. Okay? And
we'll get to that. So that is true. You don't need to
explicitly state it, but it's still the model. Okay? You might be
allowed to, so yes, but yeah, okay, yeah.
You mention חזיר. chazir.
Not might, you are, yeah, okay, go ahead.
You mention חזיר, chazir, wouldn't it be an acceptable נדר neder to
say this food is like חזיר chazir to me?
Nope. Nope. You could say this food is like בשר וחלב, basar
v'chalav, חמץ בפסח, chametz b'Pesach, חזיר, chazir, and חלב, chelev, and you
haven't done anything. Because all those things, you don't have the power
to make it like חזיר. chazir. What you have the power to
do is make it like a קרבן korban because that's an area
where you can actually through your words transform the status of something.
Like if I say it's forbidden to eat.
Absolutely. Now, if you said I'm taking on a שבועה shevuah that
I'll treat this like חזיר, chazir, right, you know, or something, but
the words still will not actually be a נדר neder to transform
the status of the object. Yes.
יפתח Yiftach when you right? So that's a נדרי מצוה?
nidrei mitzvah? That's a good point. What does it say there? It
says נדר neder by יפתח? Yiftach?
I don't know what the word נדר neder is there.
But see, again, if
you will do this for me, then I
will like the first thing that I will give it to God.
So that falls exactly into this category. Now again, in חז"ל, Chazal,
נדרי מצוה nidrei mitzvah become my personal
obligation like, like I said, go to מנין minyan every morning or
something like that. That would be a נדרי מצוה. nidrei mitzvah. That's
not the Torah's idea. The Torah's idea is an object that is
given to God. Right? So yes, that would be exactly like these
examples. I'll give you מעשר. ma'aser. I will give this animal. I
will give over this city to God. I will give the first
thing that walks out of my house. So it is the classic
נדר neder of the Torah. חז"ל, Chazal, when they defined it as
נדרי מצוה, nidrei mitzvah, it's not exactly conceptually the same point. A
נדר מצוה neder mitzvah is obligating yourself to do some מצוה, mitzvah,
okay, as opposed to giving some thing to God. Yes.
So חנה Channah saying I'll give my first child?
Yeah, that all would be in that נדר. neder. That's a good
point. I hadn't really like sort of categorized all those things, but
you're right. All of those are very similar and you'll notice that
the similarity is about a thing or person being given over to
God.
Right? Right. Yes.
Yes. Clearly פשט, peshat, the standard נדר neder in the Torah is
this. You know, and a קרבן korban fits into that model. Okay?
That's which is so ironic. This is all the standard נדר neder
of the Torah, but in rabbinic literature, the standard נדר neder becomes
the example in מטות, Matot, which is just about something forbidden without
a gift to God as part of that context. Yes.
So is every speech act הקדש hekdesh in a way is a
subset of the broader category of הפלאה? hafala? Well,
yeah, of well you can change the
status of an object through a speech act. Right? Right. But הקדש,
hekdesh, yeah, but I mean I would rather see it as נדר
neder is derivative of הקדש. hekdesh. But yes, but yeah, they're all
in that category of הפלאה. hafala. Okay. So that's in terms of
one last question.
Just for curiosity, in their introduction, they use the חפצא גברא cheftza
gavra model.
Yeah. Well, that is, I as opposed to the object. Right? Yeah.
No, that's going to be on the first דף daf of the
גמרא. Gemara. We're going to read that in a minute. But I
wanted to give it a bigger context here. Okay. So let me
say something about this מסכת. Masechet, Okay. The language of this מסכת
masechet. is different than the standard Aramaic grammatically certain terms that are
used and so on. This was already noted by תוספות Tosafot and
the ראשונים, Rishonim, רש"י Rashi etc. רש"י Rashi calls it in a
few places לשון ירושלמי. Lashon Yerushalmi. Now that raises a question about
so what's the story? Why does this have a different grammar? What
does that say about where it comes from? So this book, which
you should be aware of, called Introduction to Talmud and Midrash, is
a very sort of distilled summary of all of the scholarship on
משנה, Mishnah, תוספתא, Tosefta, the גמרא, Gemara, מדרשים Midrashim and so on.
It's actually put together by two non-Jews, Strack and Stemberger, though they
did an amazing job of distilling all of the scholarship on everything.
And they have anyway so I'll just read you some brief selection
of this on page one hundred and ninety five. Five tractates: נדרים,
Nedarim, נזיר, Nazir, מעילה, Meilah, כריתות Keritot and תמיד Tamid differ from
the rest of the Babylonian Talmud in a number of linguistic and
grammatical peculiarities which were already observed by תוספות. Tosafot.
These extraordinary tractates also include the parts of a parts of תמורה
Temurah that are characterized by the expression לישנא אחרינא. lishna achrina. So
you have particularly interesting in תמורה, Temurah, you have one passage which
sounds like your normal Aramaic, and then you have a לישנא אחרינא
lishna achrina which sounds like this different type of an Aramaic. Or
the normal Aramaic that we're very that we are familiar with. And
then it goes on and lists some of the things and you'll
notice some of the things. So what's the story about this? So
רש"י Rashi designated לישנא אחרינא lishna achrina as לשון ירושלמי, lashon Yerushalmi,
he's followed by איי הלוי, Ay HaLevi, who assumes that these reflect
Palestinian usage. Okay now, one of the things that they use to
tie that into the idea that maybe this ultimately was something that
was more from the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is the fact that and important
to note, a testimony of the גאונים. Geonim. And this is another
ספר sefer אוצר הגאונים Otzar HaGeonim which was this amazing work by
לוין Levin who collected all of the different passages of from all
the different תשובות teshuvos of the גאונים Geonim which were completely not
systematized and not organized, and he extracted every time they referenced the
גמרא Gemara and organized it by מסכתא. masechta. So anyway, he says
here he says the following: he
says
there's very little on these מסכתות. masechtos. הגאונים שקמו אחרי חתימת התלמוד,
HaGeonim shekamu achrei chatimas haTalmud, the גאונים Geonim right after the תלמוד
Talmud was sealed, ושקדו לבאר ולבנות הלכות עולם ושלא לערב בלשונות veshakdu
levaveir ulevaneis halachos olam veshelo letareiv beleshonos etc.
so that you know the גאונים Geonim who really tried to clarify
what the גמרא Gemara was talking about. הדירו עצמם ממסכת נדרים. Hiziru
atzmam mimasechet Nedarim.
They held them- they did not really involve themselves in discussing נדרים
Nedarim, בתוך המתיבתא שלהם, betoch hametivta shelahem, in their ישיבות yeshivos
this is the גאונים. Geonim. והכריזו Vehichrizu and they announced דאנן לא
גרסינן נדרים. de'anan la gersinan Nedarim.
We don't learn נדרים. Nedarim ולא ידיענא לאסור ולהתיר בה לא נדר
ולא שבועה. Velo yediana le'asur ulehateir bah lo neder velo shevuah.
And we don't know how to make things אסור assur by נדר
neder and certainly not how to make them permissible or by a
שבועה. shevuah. לפיכך אין נוהגין בישיבה ולא בכל מקום ולהתיר נדרים לא
בראש השנה ולא ביום הכיפורים. Lefikach ein nohagin biyeshiva velo bechol makom
ulehateir nedarim lo beRosh Hashanah velo beYom HaKippurim.
We don't do any התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. Okay, but it says
בארץ ישראל היו נוהגין בכך כל הימים. be'Eretz Yisrael hayu nohagin bekach
kol hayamim. Now the
why did they not do it, the one of the reasons given
and he's got a whole discussion of quotes here this is all
in the introduction. Anyway, one of the reasons given is because if
you learn it, you know, it's like when you learn מסכת קידושין
Masechet Kiddushin in high school and then you know two kids get
together and say oh this'll be fun, הרי את מקודשת לי harei
at mekudeshet li or whatever and then so if you learn this
then you start making נדרים, Nedarim. right? So if you put it
out of our sort of religious consciousness so much, you know, then
you're not making נדרים, nedarim, you don't even realize it's so much
of an option. That seems to have been a strong part of
the motivation. And by the way, this is worth noting right at
the beginning
that we don't appreciate right how much this was part of the
religious lives of people. I mean you have people making נדרים nedarim,
all the time and it's a way in which you bring God
into your world. Like it could be an attitude of a way
of dealing with people's impetus of חומרא. chumra. You want to do
more, you want to make things forbidden, you know, and the גמרא
Gemara in some place calls making a נדר neder like building a
במה. bamah. There's that sense of your own personal religiosity which could
be a good thing or a bad thing. It gives expression to
it, but you know, to what degree is it keeping within the
communal sort of norms and so on. But it was a major
part of people's religious lives and but you know, there's a lot
of ways you transgress by making a נדר neder and there's also
a strong emphasis about not making נדרים nedarim so you don't transgress.
Anyway, so there was that גאוני Geonic practice at least in בבל
Bavel not to learn it. Okay,
interestingly there are the classic ראשונים Rishonim on נדרים, nedarim maybe not
as well fleshed out, and there's a huge ר"ן Ran I'll talk
about that, but anyway it was not so much learned in the
בבל Bavel ישיבות. yeshivos. So some want to say that therefore it
really was you know primarily reflects ירושלמי- Yerushalmi it's a ירושלמי מסכתא.
Yerushalmi masecheta. That is pretty strongly debated by the other scholars and
mostly what they point out is that the standard בבלי Bavli reflects
the Babylonian- Babylonian usage in סורא, Sura, which is where רב אשי
Rav Ashi was. And this really much more reflects the Babylonian usage
in פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, which is also a lot of the גאוני Geonic
writing and therefore the speculation is that this really came from פומבדיתא.
Pumbedita. And then the question is well, you know what, parallel, same
time, earlier, later? And then there's like a lot of different speculation.
Some want to say it's earlier and it was in פומבדיתא Pumbedita
it didn't and some want to say everything started in פומבדיתא Pumbedita
but this- everything else got re-worked in סורא, Sura, this didn't get
re-worked, and this is earlier or this is parallel. And then some
want to say no, actually it's later than everything else. So there's
a whole debate, okay, but it seems that a lot that at
least to whether how you date it is one question but it
does seem that there is whether early or late but it does
seem that there's now pretty much of a consensus that the difference
of these מסכתות masechtos was that they came more from the ישיבה
yeshiva of פומבדיתא Pumbedita rather than the ישיבה yeshiva of סורא. Sura.
Okay, so that's if you want to see more that's over there.
The last thing I'll say and then we could actually start learning
the מסכת masechet is that רש"י Rashi here in no other מסכת
masechet or not very few other מסכתות masechtos do you get רש"י
Rashi with the words רש"י Rashi on the top of it. And
the reason is it's one of these things like if you have
to say it's רש"י Rashi then... Something is off, because it's not
really רש"י. Rashi. And actually, nobody knows exactly who it is, but
actually in many ישיבות Yeshivot when they learn it, they don't even
bother to read it. It's so much like not seen as like
an, you know, because it's also not as like, not only is
it not רש"י, Rashi, you know, okay, who else is רש"י Rashi
besides רש"י? Rashi? But it's like, but it's not as rigorous in
terms of like being as consistent or being as clear and being
as precise. So it often isn't even really learned. What you do
have is the ר"ן Ran who is later, 13th century. And the
ר"ן Ran is one of the clearest ראשונים, Rishonim, not one of
the most creative, although there are a few very important חידושים Chidushim
of the ר"ן, Ran, but he's one of the clearest. I often,
I sometimes call him the CliffNotes to the גמרא Gemara because he
sort of synthesizes things that the other ראשונים Rishonim says and presents
them nicely. And he's wordy as you can see, but he's very,
very clear. And the ר"ן Ran becomes like a combination רש"י Rashi
תוספות, Tosafot, like clarifying what the גמרא Gemara is saying and then
bringing in other types of discussions and contradictions and problems and resolve
things them. Along the sides you do have תוספות Tosafot and the
רא"ש, Rosh, so you do have the classic תוספות. Tosafot. So the
תוספות Tosafot here are not as, you know, they're not as like
as involved
as שקלא וטריא. Shakla Vetarya.
There's more of a sort of straightforward commentary rather than an in-depth
analysis. But you do have them, you have the ר"ן, Ran, but
you have ראשונים Rishonim interestingly, you even have a רי"ף Rif and
a רמב"ן. Ramban. The רי"ף Rif wrote הלכות Halachot on the, on
מסכת masechet נדרים, Nedarim, so so much for the גאונים Geonim not
learning it so people don't know it. The רי"ף Rif actually wrote
his הלכות, Halachot, what are the bottom line הלכות Halachot of נדרים.
Nedarim. And the רמב"ן, Ramban, and the רמב"ן Ramban does this in
a few places, particularly the more obscure topics, he also wrote הלכות
הרמב"ן Hilchot HaRamban on נדרים, Nedarim, which is printed in the back
of the גמרא Gemara paralleling the רי"ף. Rif. And then there are
all these אחרונים Achronim who write commentaries on them. So there actually
is a lot of ראשונים Rishonim although not of the same exact,
you know, character as in other מסכתות. Masechtot. All right, so that
was a lot of introduction. Now we're actually going to start learning
the מסכת. Masechet. Yeah?
Yeah, I was a little confused about, you were talking about where
this might have originated in בבל, Bavel, but then you said, you
said the גאונים Geonim didn't study but then I thought you said
also that they didn't study it in the Babylonian ישיבות. Yeshivot.
The גאוניק Geonic Babylonian ישיבות, Yeshivot, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. When I,
yeah, I didn't mean in the time of the גמרא, Gemara, because
in, right, in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they still studied it in
the גאונים Geonim period, right. So, yes.
ירושלמי נדרים? Yerushalmi Nedarim?
I believe,
that's a good point, I believe there is.
Yeah, you know, it's for, yeah, there is, because I'm just even
remembering, just shows how long it's been since I've learned נדרים Nedarim
that I'm not remembering. But yes, there is a ירושלמי
נדרים. Yerushalmi Nedarim. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So let's take a look. So we start with the first משנה.
Mishna. כל כינוי, Kol Kinnui,
you see I had to follow the ר"ן Ran who writes this
huge introduction so I gave you a whole half-hour introduction. כל כינוי
נדרים כנדרים, וחרמים כחרמים, ושבועות כשבועות. Kol kinnui nedarim kenedarim, vacharamin kacharamin,
ushvuot keshvuot.
Sounds like כל נדרי, Kol Nidrei, right? Okay, so all כינויי, Kinnuyei,
כינויי Kinnuyei are like euphemisms or nicknames, you know, words that are
not exactly the word of נדר Neder count as if you said
the word נדר Neder if it's used as a substitute word. And
the same by a חרם. Cherem. חרם Cherem is a way of
saying this object is חרם, Cherem, like, you know, given over to
God. And then there's the question what does he do? Do you
give it to the Temple? Do you give it to the כהנים?
Kohanim?
The ר"ן Ran wants to read this חרם Cherem more in, not
in the actual giving to God because that would be a קדשים
Kodashim thing, okay, and more like if you said this object is
forbidden on me like a חרם, Cherem, okay, then it really just
becomes a form of a נדר. Neder. But a נדר Neder is
making an object forbidden, classic חרם Cherem is changing the status and
giving it over to God or the
כהנים. Kohanim. ושבועות כשבועות, Ushvuot keshvuot, and if you take a כינוי
Kinnui of a שבועה, Shevua, a sort of a non-you know, not
the word שבועה Shevua but a word that's derived from it or
some variation of that word, that counts as a
שבועה. Shevua. ונזירות כנזירות, Unezirut kenezirut, and if you say a language
that's sort of refers to being a נזיר Nazir even if it's
not exactly the word of נזיר, Nazir, that counts. Now interestingly, the
משנה Mishna does not jump right ahead and give you some examples,
that would be very helpful. But if you turn your, you turn
to דף, Daf, where is it? י', Yud, I think י"א. Yud
Aleph. It's like two משניות Mishnayot later. Yeah, י', Yud, דף י',
Daf Yud, דף י', Daf Yud,
maybe three משניות Mishnayot later. It finally gives you the examples.
האומר, Ha'omer, if somebody says, people have this? י' עמוד א' Yud
Amud Aleph at the bottom? Okay. האומר קונם קונח קונס הרי אלו
כינויים לקרבן.
Ha'omer konam konach konas
harei elu kinnuyim l'korban.
Okay,
so that's the קונם. Konam. קונם Konam sounds like קרבן Korban but
in some weird variation of it. קונח קונס, Konach konas, that's a
nickname for קרבן. Korban. חרק חרך חרף הרי אלו כינויים לחרם. Cherek
cherech cheref harei elu kinnuyim l'cherem.
Okay, so it's basically...
What did the ר"ן Ran get into it? What? That's what the
ר"ן... Ran... ר"ן Ran says it on the first... Yeah, yeah, he
gets it from here.
Yeah, yeah. נזיק נזיח פזיח הרי אלו כינויים לנזירות. Nazik naziyach paziyach
harei elu kinnuyim l'nezirut. I mean, they do sound similar, right? But
some key letters are changed. שבותה שקוקה נדר במוהי, Shvuta shkuka neder
bemohi, that's
the last, that's the one that's not like any of the others.
Anyway, הרי אלו כינויים לשבועה. Harei elu kinnuyim lishvua. So all of
them they're like saying the word but sort of like saying it
in a slightly corrupt form. Now the גמרא... Gemara... Going to discuss
where these כינויים kinuyim come from and one approach
is that
they are like some other language. Of course it's very funny, how
did it work out that this other non-Hebrew language sounds just like
Hebrew with a slight different variation? You know, who knows, maybe it's
some Aramaic or Semitic language, but the more logical explanation in the
גמרא Gemara is לשון שבדו להם חכמים. lashon shebadu lahem chachamim.
It's a made-up language, okay, pig Latin, which is basically and the
rabbis tried to train people to use these terms rather than the
classic terms to be a little bit more, now you could say
two things. The way the גמרא Gemara says it is so you
don't wind up saying שם השם לבטלה. shem Hashem levatala. Because if
you say נדר, neder, you know often you'll say maybe נדר להשם
neder l'Hashem or you'll say קרבן להשם korban l'Hashem or שבועה להשם.
shvua l'Hashem. Whereas if you say a weird term נזיח, Naziach, פזיח,
Paziach, קונם, Konam, or whatever then you know you won't end it
with sort of saying להשם. l'Hashem.
I don't know but anyway that's what the גמרא Gemara says or
you could just say that it leads to greater sense of like
you know creates a technical terminology so you know that you're dealing
with the actual speech act and with this technical thing by using
the specific weird technical terminology that nobody else uses. And it also
maybe makes you a little bit more reluctant to do it because
you know it's a very it's a strange type of a language
and it's a strange terminology. So whatever it is it seems that
this sort of reluctance or hesitancy or recognizing the power of this
led to this different language and then it's saying if you use
these כינויים, kinuyim, if you use these substitute words, they count as
using the word itself.
Yes, exactly. I want to understand: בזמן הזה, bezman hazeh, if I
make a נדר neder or if I make something into a קרבן
korban even without the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it has effect because
otherwise נדרים nedarim won't have any effect really. If I say this
meat is like a קרבן korban and קרבנות korbanot don't
apply, you make something else into a קרבן. korban. And then you
use איסור מעילה, issur meila, you have to let it graze, you
can't work it whatever.
Even בזמן הזה bezman hazeh you can do that? Yeah, yeah, you
can do that, so it can't be brought, it's dedicated. Right, right.
Which is why by the way the standard examples in that משנה
Mishna of a נדר, neder, they weren't
like
נדך, nedech, נדר neder or whatever you know they were קונם, Konam,
right? It wasn't a variation of the word נדר, neder, it was
a variation of the word קרבן. korban. And that gets back to
the idea that it all hearkens to the world of קרבנות korbanot
as the type of a model. Okay, so that's point number one:
the substitute words count. Now, האומר לחברו. ha'omer l'chavero. Now interestingly the
משנה Mishna ignores does not give examples right away and goes on
to a different point. האומר לחברו מודרני ממך, ha'omer l'chavero modrani mimcha,
מופרשני ממך, mufrashani mimcha, מרוחקני ממך: meruchakani mimcha: I am you know
forbidden to you as by a vow, I am vowed from you
is literally the translation, or separated from you, or distanced from
you, okay, שאני אוכל לך she'ani ochel lach that regarding
that I will eat of yours, שאני טועם לך she'ani toem lach
or things that I will taste of yours, אסור, asur, then he
is forbidden. Now that's a very complicated language, huh? What did you
just say? It sounds like what he basically is saying
is: יאכילך. y'achilecha. Well, okay, so there's a גרסא girsa in the
גמרא, Gemara, שאני she'ani or שאיני she'eini because it's remember it focuses
on the object. So it might mean those things that I would
eat of yours. Okay, so that's going to be a question in
the גמרא: Gemara: does your saying I am vowed that I won't
eat it? But if you say that I won't eat it, you're
focusing on you, right, it's not all about you, right Mike? So
anyway, okay, it's about the object. So therefore this object is forbidden
regarding eating, right? So that's the question: שאני she'ani or שאיני? she'eini?
We'll get to that in the גמרא. Gemara. But basically it's like
your food is or you are forbidden to me, and can you
make the person like the object that you're forbidden to derive benefit
from? Right, that definitely seems sometimes how it the language is talking:
you are forbidden to me for me to derive any benefit of
eating or any benefit of tasting. Another way though of thinking about
it is all of your food is forbidden on me and so
on. Okay, so the נדר neder seems to be oriented towards the
person or his foods or objects or whatever that they become forbidden
for you to eat or to taste. And with these different languages:
מופרשני, mufrashani, מרוחקני, meruchakani, etc. Okay, now you could by the way
although the other משנה Mishna discusses כינויים kinuyim with
קונם Konam etc., you actually could have said that this is also
a כינוי. kinuy. מודרני modrani is the standard word of נדר. neder.
מופרשני, mufrashani,
מרוחקני meruchakani
are translate you know are are are are translations of them you
know or different versions of the concept of a נדר: neder: to
be separated from you, forbidden you know from you and so on.
But the גמרא Gemara does not understand that as the כינויים. kinuyim.
The כינויים kinuyim are more of these like corrupt versions of the
words, so these are all like classic נדר. neder. Anyway all of
those work. רבי Rabbi now if somebody says מנודה אני לך, menudeh
ani lach, uses the language of נידוי, niduy, which is the Rabbinic
language of excommunication, right? So it's not
exactly is that
like a דבר הנדור? davar hanadur? Is that
really is that
really like focus on like the object? He struggled, okay, he struggled
with this, you know, wrestled that maybe you need to be strict
about this type of a case. So he wasn't sure what the
הלכה halacha is, he was inclined to be strict. Now, what are
the, what's the point of the last part of the משנה? Mishnah?
The גמרא Gemara says that the last part of the משנה, Mishnah,
not the רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, we'll worry about that later, but
what's the חידוש chidush of this מופרשני ממך? mufroshani mimcha? So one
thing I would want to know is like I said, is it
the person that's forbidden or the object or the person's foodstuff or
whatever? But the גמרא Gemara is going to say that this also
is an example of another concept of נדר, neder, not called a
כינוי, kinuy, but called a יד. yad. A יד yad is a
handle. Not a hand, but it's also a handle, okay, and what
a יד yad means is that you can make a statement which
is an elliptical statement, okay, which is an abbreviated statement. And therefore
you don't even have to say the whole thing. Like the גמרא
Gemara has an example by a נזיר. Nazir. A נזיר Nazir is
walking by and one guy says, and one guy says, right, right,
one guy says, I will be, and that's somehow by context understood
to be I will be like him, I want, I will be
a נזיר. Nazir. And the גמרא Gemara just does two types of
יד, yad, ידיים מוכיחות, yadayim mochiachot, a יד yad where it's very
clear from context exactly what you meant even though you didn't exactly
say the words, and ידיים שאינן מוכיחות, yadayim she'einam mochiachot, that it
was not clear from context what you meant. You might have meant
that, but you might have meant something else. Okay, and it understands
that the last case in the משנה Mishnah is not a כינוי
kinuy because they're all good Hebrew even though they're not all the
word נדר, neder, but that it is actually a יד. yad. Why
is it a יד? yad? What are you abbreviating? Okay, so take
a look at the רן Ran here, where the רן Ran says
the very small רן, Ran, three lines from the bottom, אומר לחברו,
omer lachaveiro, it's harder to see where the רן Ran starts although
they're not big beginning words. אומר לחברו מודרני ממך. omer lachaveiro mudrani
mimcha. מפרש בגמרא דהיינו ידות. mefaresh bagemara dehainu yadot. ומפרשינן נמי דהכי
קתני, umefarshinan nami dehachi katani, מודרני ממך שאני אוכל לך מודרני ממך
שאני טועם לך. mudrani mimcha she'ani ochel lach, mudrani mimcha she'ani to'eim
lach. Okay, דהוי ידות. dehavei yadot. Why is it a יד? yad?
משום דלא מסיק דיבוריה למימר כקורבן. mishum delo masik diburei lemeimar kikorban.
So here's the question, right, going back to Chaim what you were
asking. You don't have to say כקורבן. kikorban. But maybe when you
don't say the word קונם konam or כקורבן kikorban and it's implied,
that's actually a יד. yad. Meaning the fundamental statement of a נדר
neder is דבר זה אסור כקורבן davar zeh assur kikorban or קונם
דבר זה עלי. konam davar zeh alay. If you said מודרני ממך
mudrani mimcha or מופרשני ממך, mufroshani mimcha, it only counts as a
נדר neder because implicitly it's כקורבן. kikorban. We understand that's the end
of your sentence except you didn't say it. Okay, so that's important
because that again holds out that the standard language is using the
idea of a קורבן korban and when you don't say it it
only works because it refers to that, it's an abbreviated sentence which
is understood to have that at the end of it.
אי נמי דלא אמר איסורא בהדיא. i nami delo amar issura beheya.
The other point is maybe no, you didn't say your food is
אסור עלי. assur alay. You didn't even say forbidden. You didn't even
refer to the change of status of the object. You said I
am separated from you. But a נדר neder is about changing the
status. So even if you don't say like a קורבן, korban, you
have to say it's אסור, assur, it's forbidden, and you didn't even
say forbidden. So that's why it's abbreviated because you didn't even say
the word forbidden. So this statement is an abbreviated נדר, neder, it's
clear you want to make a נדר, neder, but you didn't have
some of the key terms. You didn't have the term of forbidden
and you didn't have the term like a קורבן. korban. And I
do think it's the interesting question here Chaim going back to your
issue is, is saying כקורבן kikorban a necessary part, but we'll just
assume you meant it, or is it not a necessary part? If
you said דבר זה אסור עלי בנדר, davar zeh assur alay beneder,
let's say you said that, is that basically a full נדר neder
or is it only a נדר neder because it refers to it
implicitly suggests the idea of a קורבן? korban? So that's an important
question. And I think those are the two opinions of the רן.
Ran. Why is it abbreviated? Is it abbreviated because it doesn't have
the word קורבן korban or is it abbreviated because it doesn't have
the word forbidden? Okay, those are the two questions in the רן,
Ran, those are the two versions in the רן. Ran. Okay, so
now let us continue. The
גמרא Gemara says, okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara.
גמרא Gemara says, כל כינויי נדרים כנדרים. kol kinu’ei nedarim kinedarim. All
כינויים, kinuyim, all I have to come up with one word. Yeah,
euphemism is funny, but maybe because it also suggests you don't want
to say the word itself which might be part of the reason.
All right, we'll go with that for now. Okay, all variations maybe,
I'll try variations.
All variations of נדרים nedarim are like נדרים. nedarim. מאי שנא גבי
נזיר דלא תנא להו לכולהו? mai shna gabei nazir delo tana lehul
kulu? Now the same משנה Mishnah appears in the beginning of נזיר.
Nazir. כל כינויי נזירות כנזירות. kol kinu’ei nezirut kinezirut.
Okay, the same thing. Except when it appears in the beginning of
נזיר, Nazir, it doesn't say and by נדרים nedarim are like נדרים
nedarim and שבועות shvuos are like שבועות shvuos and חרמים cherems are
like חרמים. cherems.
It only talks about נזיר. Nazir. The first line in נזיר Nazir
is כל כינויי נזירות כנזירות kol kinu’ei nezirut kinezirut and that's all
it says. It doesn't have the whole list.
So מאי שנא גבי נזיר. mai shna gabei nazir. ומאי שנא גבי
נדרים דקתני לכולהו? u’mai shna gabei Nedarim diksani lekulu? Listed all these
cases: נדר, neder, נזיר, Nazir, חרם, charem, שבועה. shvua. משום דנדר ושבועה
כתיבי גבי הדדי, mishum de’neder u’shvua ksivi gabei hadadi, because since נדר
neder and שבועה shvua are written by next to one another, איש
כי ידור נדר או השבע שבועה, ish ki yidor neder o hishavei
shvua, so if you're going to talk about נדר, neder, you want
to talk about שבועה. shvua. Okay, so therefore once, and once we're
talking about נדר neder and שבועה, shvua, we might as well fill
out the list. Okay,
ותני תרתי, ve’tani tarti, so it said נדר neder and שבועה shvua
because those usually go as a combo. וכיון דתני תרתי, ve’keivan detani
tarti, if it's going to say those two, תני לכולהו, tani lekulu,
we might as well now just give the whole list of all
the things that this idea of כינויים kinnuyim apply to. וליתני כינוי
שבועות בתר נדרים, u’lisni kinnuy shvuos basar nedarim, if it's because נדר
neder and שבועה shvua go together, why did it say כינוי נדרים
כנדרים, kinnuy nedarim kenedarim, חרמים כחרמים, charamim kecharamim, שבועות כשבועות? shvuos keshvuos?
Why did it have נדר, neder, חרם, charem, שבועה? shvua? If it's
because נדר neder and שבועה shvua go together, it should have said
נדר neder and שבועה shvua first as a pair. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, איידי דתני נדרים, aidi detani nedarim, and now we
get to the big point, which is דמיתסר חפצא עליה. demis’ar heftza
alei. It started with נדר, neder, which is making the object, the
חפץ, heftz, the object forbidden on you. תנא נמי חרמים, tana nami
charamim, so it gave the example of a חרם, charem, דמיתסר חפצא
עליה, demis’ar heftza alei, which makes the object that you are making
חרם, charem, banned, forbidden, given over to God, that's also making the
object forbidden. So that is similar. חרם charem is a type of
a נדר neder essentially. לאפוקי שבועה, la’apukei shvua, and therefore it pushed
off mentioning שבועה, shvua, because שבועה shvua is different. דקאסר נפשיה מן
החפצא. de’kasar nafshia min hacheftza. You are making yourself forbidden to, even
if it's about eating this food, a שבועה shvua could be about
doing a lot of things, but even if it's about whether I'm
going to eat this loaf of bread, a נדר neder says the
loaf of bread becomes a forbidden object. A שבועה shvua says I
won't eat the loaf of bread. So therefore we want to have
נדר neder and חרם charem together and שבועה shvua later. So right
upfront, as with many מסכתות, masechtos, okay, they open with like an
opening סוגיא sugya which focuses on really a relatively trivial point, okay,
like, okay, why did it have the full list here and not
there? I mean, that's an interesting academic point, but whatever. Anyway, but
then it uses this as a way of bringing in some important
concepts that are going to be relevant for the מסכתא. masechta. And
this one does it probably more than almost any other מסכתא, masechta,
gives you the punchline right there to begin with. The basic difference
between the object and the person is like the most basic conceptual
distinction and focus of this מסכתא. masechta. You know, that שבועה shvua
is about the person, this is about the object, and all of
this is about changing the status of the object. All right, so
פתח בכינויים. patach bekinnuyim. Now it has another question. It starts with
the examples of כינויים kinnuyim about variations of the words. כל כינוי
נדרים כנדרים, kol kinnuy nedarim kenedarim, and then ומפרש ידות. u’mefaresh yados.
It doesn't give the כינויים, kinnuyim, that's a משנה mishna later on
דף י: daf yud: נזיח נזירא, neziach nazira, קונם קונח konam konach
or whatever. And but what it does give is a different concept
of a יד, yad, of a handle, of abbreviated sentences. הריני ממך
מודרני ממך, hareini mimcha mudrani mimcha, and as we said, that's abbreviated
either because it doesn't have the word איסור, issur, forbidden, this becomes
the forbidden object, or it doesn't have the word קונם konam or
קורבן, korban, it doesn't refer to the קורבן. korban. So why did
it skip over giving you examples of כינויים kinnuyim and go right
away to the idea of יד, yad, abbreviated
statements? ותו, u’su, and in addition, ידות איניש, yados inish, it forgot
about ידות? yados? Why did it give an example of יד yad
without telling me the הלכה halacha of יד? yad? Right, it's two
questions: it speaks about כינויים kinnuyim and gives me an example of
יד. yad. So why didn't it give me an example of כינויים,
kinnuyim, and if you're going to talk about ידות, yados, talk about
ידות, yados, don't just start with the example, talk about the rule.
What did it do, forget about them?
חסורי מחסרא, chasorei mechasra,
yeah, it means to forbid, right, not people, forget. Okay, so רש"י
Rashi says no, חסורי מחסרא, chasorei mechasra, it was talking about
ידות, yados, וחסורי מחסרא והכי קתני, ve'chasorei mechasra ve'hachi kasani, and it
was missing some words, and here is how you have to read
it: כל כינוי נדרים כנדרים וידות נדרים כנדרים, kol kinnuy nedarim kenedarim
ve'yados nedarim kenedarim, all, you know, variations of the words count as
a
נדר, neder, and abbreviated נדרים nedarim count as נדרים. nedarim. Okay, and
then it's going to give you examples of the abbreviated נדרים, nedarim,
of the ידות. yados. So if we stick in that line that
isn't there, then the examples follow that line.
The whole thing is a יד. yad.
Well said, right, the whole משנה mishna is a יד. yad. לפרש
כינויי ברישא, lifrosh kinnuyei beraysha, all right, even if I want to
concede that maybe it implied, as Dov nicely said, it was a
יד, yad, it implied the idea of ידות, yados, why not still
give the examples of the first thing you mentioned? Start with the
examples of כינויים kinnuyim and then go on to the examples of
ידות. yados. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, ההוא דסליק מיניה, ההוא מפרש ברישא. hahu desalik
minei, hahu mefaresh beraysha. No, it wants to pick up on the
one it mentioned at the end. Of course, the irony is it
didn't mention it, but if you accept the editing of the משנה,
mishna, then it mentioned it. So basically, you know, it's the chiastic
structure. Is it AB AB, which is what the גמרא Gemara is
saying: give the rule of A, the rule of B, examples A,
examples B? Is it AB BA, right? You say here's the rule
of A, here's the rule of B, and then the first examples
you start are with the last case you mentioned, which is sometimes
a structure as we're about to see that occurs in the משנה.
mishna. The irony here is that it was a יד. yad. it
could say that it wants to give the examples of B because
it most recently mentioned B, but it only mentioned B because we
inserted that line in the משנה, Mishnah, it wasn't really there. But
okay. So that's why we wanted to give examples of the ידות
Yadot because we implicitly had somehow already mentioned ידות. Yadot. All right.
So גמרא Gemara says, one minute. תנא מפרש ברישא? Tana mefaresh berisha?
Did it not,
and here's an example where we do this chiastic structure. במה מדליקין
ובמה אין מדליקין. Bameh Madlikin u'vameh ein Madlikin.
What do you like, can you use to light for candles on
שבת Shabbos and what can't you use? אין מדליקין, Ein Madlikin, and
then it starts with things you can't use, right? A B B
A. במה טומנין ובמה אין טומנין. Bameh Tomnin u'vameh ein Tomnin. What
can you sort of insulate your food with on שבת Shabbos and
what not? אין טומנין, Ein Tomnin, it gives you the things you
can't. במה אשה יוצאה ובמה אינה יוצאה. Bameh isha yotzah u'vameh einah
yotzah.
What can a woman wear on שבת, Shabbos, like without if there's
no עירוב, Eruv, because some things she can't wear, we're afraid that
she'll take it off to show her friends, like a hat or
a pin or whatever? So what can she not wear? ולא תצא
אשה, V'lo tetze isha, and it starts with the things that she
can't wear. So therefore we have this as a pattern. So גמרא
Gemara says, one minute. וכל היכא דפתח לא מפרש ברישא? V'chol heicha
depatach lo mefaresh berisha? Are you telling me anytime it opens with
something, it says A B, it won't, it won't give examples of
A first? I'll give you times it does A B A B.
והתנן. Ve'hatnan. יש נוחלין ומנחילין, Yesh Nochlin u'Manchilin,
there are some that can inherit and bequeath. נוחלין ולא מנחילין, Nochlin
velo Manchilin, and there are those that can inherit but cannot bequeath.
Okay, what's an example, I mean inherit and bequeath is obvious, what's
somebody who can inherit but not bequeath? It is a relationship of
a son and a mother, right? A son can inherit from his
mother, but the mother doesn't inherit from the son. Okay, so that's
that because you know because again sort of it goes by the
patriarchal lines. Okay, as opposed to a father and son, right? A
son inherits from his father, but if the son dies first and
he doesn't have any brothers, then the father inherits from the son.
Okay, so יש נוחלין ומנחילין נוחלין ולא מנחילין, Yesh Nochlin u'Manchilin, Nochlin
velo Manchilin, and then it starts with the A. ואלו נוחלין ומנחילין,
V'elu Nochlin u'Manchilin, these are the ones that both inherit and bequeath.
Okay, so that's A B A B. יש מותרות לבעליהן ואסורות ליבמיהן,
Yesh mutarot l'va'aleihen va'asurot l'yivmeihen, there are some wives that are permissible
to their husbands but forbidden to their brothers-in-law. If an אלמנה Almanah
is married to a כהן Kohen and the brother is a כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, then he can't do ייבום Yibum because
this wife well she anyway becomes an אלמנה Almanah because her husband
the guy dies. Anyway, okay, so that's a woman anyway that's permissible
to her husband but forbidden to the ייבום. Yibum. מותרות ליבמיהן ואסורות
לבעליהן Mutarot l'yivmeihen va'asurot l'va'aleihen or the reverse. If an אלמנה Almanah
is married to a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the marriage is binding
but she's forbidden to her husband, but if he dies then the
brother-in-law can do ייבום Yibum because the brother is just a normal
כהן. Kohen. Okay, so that's A B. ואלו מותרות לבעליהן ואסורות ליבמיהן.
V'elu mutarot l'va'aleihen va'asurot l'yivmeihen. And then it starts with the A,
okay, with the first example, permissible to their husband forbidden to their
brother-in-law. יש טעונה שמן ולבונה, Yesh te'unah shemen u'levonah,
there are some מנחות Menachos that you have to have both oil
and frankincense. שמן ולא לבונה, Shemen v'lo levonah, and some have oil
without frankincense. ואלו טעונה V'elu te'unah and that's a מנחת נסכים. Minchat
Nesachim. ואלו טעונה שמן ולבונה, V'elu te'unah shemen u'levonah, these are the
ones that have oil and frankincense. So it goes A B A.
יש טעונה הגשה
ואין טעונה תנופה, Yesh te'unah hagashah v'ein te'unah tenufah, there are some
קרבנות Korbanot that you touch them to the corner of the מזבח
Mizbeach of the altar and you don't wave them.
What, did we make the point already?
Yes, I think so. But anyway, isn't this fun? Okay, and they
don't require waving. יש טעונה הגשה ואין טעונה תנופה, Yesh te'unah hagashah
v'ein te'unah tenufah, תנופה ולא הגשה, Tenufah v'lo hagashah, some require waving
and not touching to the altar. ואלו טעונות הגשה, V'elu te'unot hagashah,
and the following require touching. So it's A B A. יש בכור
לנחלה ואין בכור לכהן, Yesh bechor l'nachala v'ein bechor l'Kohen, there are
some who are considered to be a firstborn in terms of getting
the double portion but would not be a firstborn for a כהן.
Kohen. What would be the example in terms of פדיון הבן? Pidyon
HaBen? A child born, a boy born after a miscarriage. Okay, it's
not פטר רחם, Peter Rechem, it's not the breaching of the womb
of the mother because there was a miscarriage, but it is the
first viable child and son of and therefore he would get a
double portion. יש בכור לנחלה
ואין בכור לכהן, Yesh bechor l'nachala v'ein bechor l'Kohen, בכור לכהן ואין
בכור לנחלה, Bechor l'Kohen v'ein bechor l'nachala, or firstborn for a כהן
Kohen but not for the inheritance. That's easy. A כהן Kohen already
has a firstborn son, and this is the firstborn son of another
wife. So therefore because it's firstborn to his mother, it's a פדיון
הבן. Pidyon HaBen. Okay, right? Because that goes by the mother. But
because it's not the firstborn for the כהן, Kohen, he doesn't get
a double portion. Okay. ואיזהו בכור לנחלה ואין בכור לכהן? V'eizehu bechor
l'nachala v'ein bechor l'Kohen? Which is the one that is firstborn for
inheritance and not for the כהן? Kohen? So it's A B A.
All right, so we have lots of examples of both. So what's
the rule? So גמרא Gemara says, הני משום דאבשי להו מפרש ההוא
דפתח ברישא. Hanei mishum d'avshei lehu mefaresh hahu depatach berisha. It does
A B A B when it's going to be like long. If
there's going to be a long discussion and a long list, right,
if you're doing A B B A, right, since you're getting to
that chiastic structure, when you get to that final A, you can't
have had too much between, between that, right? Because the A is
way up A B B, if there's going to be a long
discussion by the time you get to the examples of A you've,
you know, forgotten the rule. So if it's going to be a
long discussion, you have to do A B A B. You're only
can do a chiastic structure if it's a tighter, shorter discussion.
The example what can an animal wear on its body on שבת
Shabbos and what not, דלא אפשה, de-lo afsha, there's not a lot
of discussion there in the משנה, Mishna, דקתני יוצא גמל, de-katani yotzei
gamal, and it still does the ABAB structure. So it's not like
there's an inclination, you know, predisposition to do chiastic unless it can't.
Sometimes it does an ABAB even though there's no particular reason. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא לאו דוקא, ella lav davka, fine, there's
no rule. זימנין דמפרש דפתח
ברישא, zimnin de-mafarash de-patach be-reisha, sometimes it starts with what it began,
ABAB. זימנין ההוא דסיים מפרש
ברישא, zimnin hahu de-sayeim mafarash be-reisha, sometimes ABBA, and our משנה Mishna
decided to discuss first the example of ידות yadot and do the
ABBA structure again, even though the first B was sort of missing.
Okay, we will continue with this tomorrow to get into the issue
of ידות yadot and כינויים. kinuyim.